Well, hello,...I'm andrew white...I'm going to
talk to-you about resource management primarily memory and cpu.
And, how it affects your app and how your
app can take advantage of memory and cpu policies?
So, first we'll look at why you should even pay any attention to this tool why does it matter to
you and why do you actually have to do anything about it?
And, I'll look at all of the things that policy covers it mainly covers memory...cpu all memory and cpu the
most critical things that covers...lots of other things as well.
And,...look at the rationale behind this why the system does this and what
is trying to do in policing these resources and look at the structure of
how it's implemented so you can see how it's trying to achieve the goals
of resource policy, policy does very it's
...a single resource manager on the system across all of windows ten and,
there's a single policy but the policy values change?
According to the skew and according to the device and,
I can also change dynamically according to the conditions the arise that runtime.
And,...at some code because this isn't just something that's
and imposed externally on your app it's something that you're at can
take advantage of or not you can take part in this and you can cooperation
you can use it to...
Or you can completely ignore it which tends to be
the less good choice and look at...look at the code options you have any api?
So, why should your...attention to this?
We making some assumptions here my first
assumption is that you want to target...
of a sensible range of different devices so it's possible that you actually
want target all possible windows ten devices
across all possible skews across mobile and desktop and
coyote and xbox and holler...and,
every single device within the skews.
That's somewhat unlikely
...heavily possible for some types of apps but for most steps you probably targeting
a subset of that-you might target like all of desktop every single desktop
device that runs windows ten what might be a combination it all of desktop and all of
...people desktop plus xbox or...some permutation the
point is that these this is a very wide range of devices.
Even within one skew is a wide range of devices you can imagine a desktop pc there isn't
a single thing it's it ranges from a pc that might have only.
One gig of physical ram
and a tiny page file and really slow disk and...screen
although up to something that has maybe hundred-twenty aching of physical ram and
a huge fast disclose lots of page file
the queries dynamically and the and multiple...screens.
there's a big range even within one skewed and if you go across skews the range gets even bigger.
The assumption is that you want you to targets more than just one single device and therefore you
can have to accommodate different device configurations
different memory different screen resolution different networking capabilities
different keyboard mouse hardware so on.
And, it's not just something that you plan up-front for a particular device
and once installed that says because things change
the runtime as well.
So, even though you say well I'm targeting this...devices with have and minimum memory
...of x and a minimum screen resolution of y
...it must have a mouse and it must have wi-fi it must have whatever
...these things can change even within the things that you consider important to around.
And, the changes fall into three.
Broad buckets what I'm what I'm calling hardware changes so you
install your app on a devices got to giga of physical ram and then the user instill
...memory...they had more memory and they take some out will they install an additional
...or...external screen oryou know,
so, those things can change and you would want to take advantage of more memory and equally you
would want to adjust yourself in the face of memory going away...
You wouldn't want to just fall over and stop working.
And, then the second bucket encoding connectivity because it includes things like
network connectivity on the strength of the connection the speed of the connection but
also things like can a cellular data and ...my in a roaming the.
And, then state changes...changes that a particular to the windows platform
where.
Things can change depending on what you're doing.
So, for example, if you're if you're.
Foreground app with you why the uses interacting with actively in the foreground
then resource policy says that you'll get a certain amount of memory or up to a certain
amount of memory...use a switches away and navigate to some other app than the previous
up is no longer the foreground app is no longer being interactively is so,
it's resource.
Grunts change it...less memory might get less
cpu it might not have the same access to critical the
...on the device that it would have otherwise so things can change
...runtime according to the state of the art and then use
...switch back again and, dual previous up not comes back into the
...and then it gets again the change mike and the other direction like it more memory you might get more cpu.
So, you're up it pays you to pay attention to the conditions that you
find on the device and to continue to pay attention as these conditions change.
...a couple of fairly obvious things as well that the consequences of
...paying attention or not paying attention one is the battery the
wall of shame so the system reports in the y to the user so they
can see the energy consumption of the each...particular when apps
go above certain critical thresholds we consider them to be.
Very energy conservative apps very energy intensive apps so you
generally you prefer your out not to show up on that list a tool for at least if it
does show up to show up with a very small bar saying it's not using very much energy
because if it does show up on that list...it uses a lot of energy there's
...the risk that the user will turn off your apple toward on installed
it because they may have a preference for battery lifetime score.
Reduce energy consumption over whatever features your app is providing.
And,...would want to pay attention so that you
don't you don't do one of the to extremely that crash.
So, for example, if you're if you're making excessive memory allocations you will eventually
get...out of memory exception if you handle that is propagated
too and you can handle and then you can continue on if you don't if you just ignore it
...you apple be terminated and from the uses perspective that looks like...crash.
The other end of the...the flip side of the bad behavior is where you
...crash but...consuming so much in terms of resources
so much memory so much cpu so much network bandwidth this guy the
...rest of the system slows down.
And, again, the user...see that eventually they'll figure out that your app is
his badly behaved and they will in a there is a...that they will on install it.
So, what you want to do is to take full advantage the system
is all the features that has available to without negatively
affecting the system without negatively affecting the overall user experience?
So, the system polices resource constraints
the on most devices resources well,
...all devices resources a finite even if you consider a huge desktop
Hundred-twenty eight gig of ram and massive hottest
...still in limit to how much is actually available and the user can
keep on installing additional physical ram up to a point...still
...limit somewhat and certainly at the bottom into the scale the constraints
...very severe so if you...the five twelve make.
Mobile device it's got very little memory to start ways it's got a very
small very slow page file typically.
And, then...everything in between.
So, we have to manage these finite resources in the face of
multiple apps multiple background tasks wanting to run concurrently so,
there's associate resource contention and what we try to do is to maintain
a balance in the user experience say that we
dainty ground full resources to any one
apple anyone task it's not a single tasking systems even though the
users interacting with some app in the foreground we don't give that
foreground up everything on the system because that would mean other things that
the uses expecting...be happening so they expect to be able
to receive incoming...or skunk vote...they expect the
email to sink in the background if they if they...a download or...expect that to continue
and to make progress in the background even the they might be doing something else in the
photographed so we try to balance all of the things that could be happening and we
give we...more resources to some things
in some situations and bless resources to other things in other situations and things change?
Depends on the type of task that it is and how it fits into the balance of
the user experience what is actually doing for the user whether,
whether the user is aware of is?
And,...he's interacting with...directly or is simply aware of it is not necessarily
directly interacting with it and then things...other...scale which they know happen sometimes but
...not quite sure when...even away and they didn't they didn't see it happening?
And, in balancing all of these
different competing resource requirements we want to achieve predictability so that
the user can expect things to happen even though they're not directly
interacting with them and say that the app knows what to expect the
...we provide enough api surface say that the app can icy figure out
what's going on can respond to changes can get notifications when things that
affect change.
And, can react accordingly?
Instead of just falling over unexpectedly.
So, I mentioned already that's the
main things that policy covers is memory and cpu?
But, we also police task lifetime so different types of
task get to run for different length of time.
And, we also police access to certain device sensors like the microphone and the
camera and the speech synthesis so on
...a few other things that we police as well as all passive providing
this holistic experience where we balance the competing requirements of different tasks
...view to maintaining the
...expectations and meeting uses expectations.
So, memory first of all this is just an example and
...don't pay too much attention to the specific numbers you can imagine
...since we covermultiple skews and all of the devices within,
within that skew the matrix of possible values huge.
So, don't worry too much about the specific values just look at the example math that's going on here?
If we take the.
The first column the five twelve make phone example...follow
...down so you can see what the math is that we using this is obviously very simplified but
we look at the device starts with five hundred twelve mega physical...
We look at the paging level on the device known this device it's going to supporter two
...fifty six make page file
but typically on these devices the storage devices slow.
So, we can't use all of the page file we can generally use up to...eighty percent of
...before the system is thrashing so
badly that performances is actually worse than if we use less of the page file.
we assumearound about eighty percent of that to fifty-six to give us two hundred we
...that off and that's a base that's what was that the...
physical constraints we have no more resource than that that's a finite resources in memory.
And, then we look at the things which are pretty much guaranteed reservations
...of...package if there is one the operating system itself the drive is the
system services all of these things are effectively on pennies but they take
up memory?
So, we allow for those...we allow for some things that we do
...but we have to pretty much guarantee says if the oem
all the mobile operator has deployed
...service agent on the device then that has
...has to run if you've got...from...has to run you have to be able to taken incoming call.
...that the tasks managing the incoming call has to run because otherwise by the
time we is not running the time we started up the other end the serve all of drop the
...because the delays too long so we have to keep this thing running the...again if you have...and
that everything has to go through...and therefore that has to be running so there's some critical carve
out so that.
The subtract from the available memory.
...take the physical...page file we subtract all of the guaranteed...
What we have left is what we use for everything else?
...the foreground...for all of the background tasks.
For the back stack for things like task completion so
...you can see in this example and remember I said that way too much about
specific numbers but this is a fairly typical example on a five twelve make
mobile device that reese's we had seven twelve to start we've...five and
twenty-three that leases with a hundred and eighty nine we've given a hundred and eighty five to the for
when up which means is format ogg if we're lucky for.
Apps in the back stack apps doing task completion in the background any background tasks of
any kind ...critical ones which isn't a lot so,
you think this is not a not a sustainable the matrix
of memory usage and, it isn't generally but then also generally this
is worse-case scenario...if everything on this list
was using the maximum that we know it normally uses all the time
some of these things we have pretty good numbers on like the
...os the drives and services those...those
a policed prior to ship so we know how big those thingswe know how much they...when they spike
and under what conditions so we've got a pretty good handle on the size of those things?
We've also got a pretty good handle...sizes acoustical manage services like
the service agents and voip and vp n and, those do have caps imposed on them so we know they can't go above
the caps and they typically actually approach...caps...the time.
So, we the what coming out for
them is very tight fit to what they're actually using most of the time.
It's the things that...that we that we have a little more leeway with give the for
...hundred...meg as a cap but,
most steps don't use that most...use half of that most of the time so it's really
a percentages game we assume that some high percentage of the time
...the user experience will be protected because most of...time the app
...running is not can be consuming up to is maximum cap and therefore
the will be something left over for the less critical background tasks.
The running in the background the and typically they will have a lot more than
...meg most the time.
And, then if you look at the other examples
...one gig tabitha things free...a little...have a little more memories play with.
After everything has been carved out reserved but then again the...not companies bigger...is partly it's
...it's almost a circular calculation but we look at telemetry data
...apps that have been deployed and, see how much they actually consume
in the wild to figure out what would be a reasonable cap for a for foreground...and what would be a
reasonable cap for every different us time?
And, then if you look at the last column the to
gig desktop we seem to have lots of extra memory floating around despite a huge.
Cap on the for...but don't forget that on this social device the
uses going to expect be running multiple...apps at the same time.
...on a small mobile they went they know that they switch from one to the next and they
...the appearance the perception of multiple apps
running at the same time but typically there aren't whereas on a desktop typically there are.
So, we have to balance all of those different user
expectations across different devices with the physical characteristics of those devices.
So, memory is the main thing but we also police cpu usage and
life-time and a few other things I mentioned so
here's again just a few simple examplesthe default background task
...not doing anything very much might be updating alive tile...
Sixteen meg memory cap it any gets to run for thirty seconds at a time...to complete all
...working thirty seconds which if you think in cpu time terms is an awfully long-time
...thirty seconds wall...
At innovative ten percent cpu usage.
So, it can do an awful lot of work in that time and,...be more than one running at the same time.
other things we penny...blocked in...service if the if the uses turned on the battery...
the feature they can disable enable disable most background
...times ...on a pair up basis.
Whereas some things like voip
...these things are not...if the if the battery savers enabled these things continue to run.
And, also the lifetime cap for these things is infinite there is no
...so...koran forever for as long as a user wants to run for that
can run unlike most background tasks...which have some kind of limits on them.
And, this is just a small set of the different tasks types on one particular
device configuration you can imagine the matrix of different tasks types with the
different memory caps the different life-time the different cpu closures and
other constraints the...is very large.
Another aspect to how we police policy is...priorities
so we look all the different scenarios in a situation where there is no contention where,
you know, there's just a few things running or maybe any
one thing running there's plenty of resources then the priorities and
the relevant the any come into play when there is contention so, if we have multiple things
running at the same time we have...up we have maybe background audio playing maybe
there's vp and running and couple of other background tasks and...bluetooth.
Or sense a task running.
And, then we get a request to act face another task.
Of some kind.
What we do is we look at that task
...look at the priority...been assigned to that task?
And, we look at the priorities of everything that's running.
So, if we don't have the resources...typically the memory for the memory for this new
activation we look at everything that's running and if we see things running that
of lower priority then the incoming...type.
Then we will terminate those things of low priority in order to meet the requirements
of the incoming activation request and we'll.
Terminate just enough of them to free up just enough resources so this new thing can run.
And, this is wide that there's, there's kinda to categories is all of the important stuff at the
top which also tend to have the to permanent memory carve...but these things
are guaranteed so those things won't get...
But, things the bottom will things with any lower priority than two and,
the number again is arbitrary and this is a this is a
sub-set again so there's a lot more priorities but,
we'll terminate things that are not quizzical so that the opportunistic tasks types
will be terminated if we need to for a higher priority incoming request.
If we get a request for...and there
is nothing currently running that's of lower priority.
Then we bouncer
request back to the whoever hospice to launch this thing which is typically the
...in the...or companion the foreground same...launch this thing...could be a background,
background task manager we say well we can't give you resources nowdo you want to
wait and it's up to the...for this task type to decide whether wants to wait
...some sometimes times it makes sense to...if it's a periodic background
tasks that files every thirty minutes and we asked to wait for
a few minutes tweet resources that's probably fine it can wait if it's some super critical
thing...must be activated right now like maybe even something
of middling importance like a like a geo fence trigger if we
don't respond to this within some period of time if we can...the task within reasonable period of time
...probably not useful anymore so again it's up to the different tasks type
is to whether the request is his queued...
deferred until there are resources...on the floor?
As a note here I mentioned that some things change dynamically so priorities actually one of
the things that mostly doesn't change but sometimes it does.
So, for example, background transfer if you have ...running and it kicks off a background
...the background transfer will run in the background that because it's positive
for ground-up experience will be given...so that can complete sooner.
If on the other hand is running as part of it background operation ...is given a
much lower priority so it depends on the context
...civil tasks like this square...priority actually there is.
Another thing I mention the policy controls is
access to certain sensitive device resources like the microphone
the camera speech synthesis and speech recognition and most of these
are privacy issues so if you're running in the background this is an example of a background
agent...audio agent during the background you typically a not allowed to use microphone
all the camera because that would be a privacy issue if you if you
were recording sounds.
In the background or taking photos in the background which the user
wouldn't necessarily be aware off me they know when it's happening if...in a
...and that's the choice but, if it's running in the background late necessary no
the thing is happening a tool so we wouldn't want to be able to.
Use critical resources like that without their knowledge so these thingsa gated by the resource manager
...remember this can change.
Depending on whether...has in the for under the background.
Ok, let's look at some code.
...look at the codes to use the protected resources is pretty straightforward there's a
lot of different api is for each of the different resource types.
then the memory management energy manager api is a very similar to each other delivery and,
they provide enough information enough finer-grained information
few to make sensible choices either during development as part of your
and diagnostics or is part of diagnostics house in the
wild in production as part of your in telemetry or just to react
in a less finer-grained way to changing conditions?
...them so here's some examples of deliveries
put everything or a lot of things all-in-one one slide here this is
examples of api is that you would use to check whether you have access
to particular resource and remember these things can change.
So, the top there's an example of some events that you might want to listen to.
Like when the network status changes.
...don't have a to actually
have any connectivity tool and if so what kind of connectivity what speed of I got.
The battery the state of the battery is it you don't have a battery if I have a battery in what
state is what state of charges that
...charging depleting and then there's a whole range
...is again it's just a small subset of different classes that represent senses
like the jerome itu and accelerometer and the compass and the camera and various other things you
would typically get hold of the thing and then check to see if it's now
because.
It might be no either because...isn't one on the device which you will
...want to know all because you don't have access to that saying at this particular point in time.
In some cases you might want to even though you've got hold of the thing in the first-place you might want to continue to
work with it surrounded by try catches because you might have got it while you were
in the foreground and...transition to the background and you continue to try and use this thing but you won't be
able to necessarily once you've gone to the background so you should
even though you've got hold of it successfully in the first and,...the foreground in the first-place
you should check periodically check if you get notifications to say things have changed.
Battery has another example get the battery reports it could be the
...battery which case we're not going to get
...capacity but if there is a battery we might want to look at the
...see how much charge we have left and then we can use that to decide whether or not we
want to do some operation that we know is very energy intensive.
Network connectivity.
You can get the user's profile and you can check things like,
you know, is...how we roaming how are we in relation to
a data limit...the data over the days image and
...behavior in accordance you would not want to do things that are
going to use more bandwidth if you're approaching or even if you're over the data limit?
All of these things you just have to check
...at the first-place check when things change listen for change
notifications thank just assume that you've you have access to
...of these things I may not even be physically present on the device.
Memory api who had memory api is in prev releases of
...windows phone.
These are been brought forward and extended so there's more things that you can get more properties and
methods on the on the api this is
the windows system windows dot system dot memory manager class.
So, there's some events we'll tell you when your memory usage is increasing and
we'll tell you when it's decreased so you can track that you can see where the old memories growing
...can each time you're told that it's growing you can check to see what it is and see whether you
want to do anything about it or not...you want to new behavior.
You can find out what
your campaigns the app memory usage limits you can find your current usage.
Or see subtracting one of the other gives you the amount of bedroom you have to play with.
you might want to do this on a on a period of time particularly during development you want to
track.
The memory consumption of certain operations and the memory trends to see if
you're continually increasing which suggests that might be a leak somewhere perhaps.
So, there there's some very simple properties you can access from the memory
manager is also a method get up and we reports which qc even
more detailed information it breaks down the usage.
And, the limit both relate to a
combination of privates plus shared commit.
But, you can get the private commit on its own if you want.
The total commit usage is going to be the same as the app...usage.
The title...going to be the same as the
...memory usage from it but this you can...either if you any interest in those
...query those properties directly if you want to get all of these things all at once
in an atomic way, you know, that this thing is taking a snapshot
...exactly the same time is this...them...cola method.
And, there are more this isn't actually an exhaustive list of the
methods and properties are a few more and, here as well this just to give an example of the sorts of things that you can get
sorts information you can get some of them will be more useful
during development to back-up your memory profiling works
a doing some of them will be directly useful hat runtime in production and.
The energy manager has a similar
...similar design.
There's actually two there's a background energy manager which I'm
illustrating here...program energy manager so you use
the background energy manager in a background task and use...manager...up.
And, again, we will give you a notifications when
your energy usage crosses certain interesting thresholds.
You can see there are
...hopefully meaningfully named values here.
Like your usage is aloe
...usage level you're near...acceptable europe...except tools and
...acceptable is level that we consider to be reasonable for
a task under normal circumstances so...point.
...that level will be just below that level...to the time but,
you can go above that level...the.
Assuming that or other resources still available to...memory and
lifetime and cpu and you could go above that what we consider to be an acceptable level
...it's a fairly arbitrary level of what
makes tasks do most of the time but you can go above it...tell you when
you've gone about it and you cross the next interesting threshold and you can continue to go above it but
...comes a point where you're going to reach and what we call
determination level and when...nearly at determination level this is
your last chance this is your last notification before we terminate?
It's very unlikely that most tasks...going to get to that level because this is
set such a high-level that you would have to be training the battery at a very fast
But, we put this in place so that if you are draining the battery it very fast rate
you can mitigate your behavior you can
tone it down if you want to if you don't then will terminate?
Well, I should I should call out that any certain types of background task
...terminated foreground...energy manager doesn't have a
termination level because we don't terminate full...up you can use much energy like in the foreground
obviously you...a good citizen it's still up to you to tuner behavior so that
you don't use lots of energy if you can avoid it but, you know,
the for run-up so we will allow you to consumes...like whereas in the background
...it will only be filled long-running background tasks as well
short running tasks cannot reach the excessive levels
is just not physically possible but, a long-running task could
...doing something that's that significantly degrading battery usage over a long
period of time then we'll consider terminating but, again,
as I say it's unlikely that may...get to that level.
Mention before that policy varies...in multiple dimensions varies by skew
so if you consider windows ten covers mobile desktop pollens
coyote xbox the physical characteristics of the devices that support a
skews on different so, mobile devices run from five twelve
make device with very small storage and low-resolution screen
up to the tablets that could have sixteen giga physical rum
...kind of a large fast page file it could have much high-resolution screen.
The desktop range overlaps that because destitute desktops in theory you
can have a desktop device that has one giga physical.
But, you could also have a desktop...has two hundred twenty eight
...giga physical and all the permutations in-between of physical
memory and page file size and speed of disk and screen resolution so on.
And, then devices like ...and xbox currents sit in the middle in the sense that
there is...one gig...answer is no one gig xbox.
... five twelve gig xbox so they come into some sort of middle of
the range decree there's no two-hundred-and-fifty six gig xbox.
Download the bottom from my perspective with my resource manager hat on
...the bottom of the scale all devices that
pretty much the same to me so a...one
getting phone...one gig tablet and a one gig desktop device
...one-k coyote device in terms of the available memory the
availability of page file...the performance that page file the screen resolution so, on
...pretty much the same to me so the resource policies is almost
identical down at that level across all skews.
But, then it starts to diverges you got the scale is to get more resources
available and better resources available on bigger devices then the
policies diverge across the different scales.
The key factor in deciding policy is the amount of available
commit which means physical plus page file but, we also
look at the screen resolution we look at other things to decide what kind of devices
is screen resolutions important because the higher-resolution the more
memories tied up in graphics buffers which are allocated on your behalf
in europe and...perhaps tend to if...running this exact same up on a device that has the
exact same memory but has a different screen resolution
...graphics memory usage will be different we have to factor that intocalculations.
We also very policy by of technology so there's,
there's existing policy in place that has been in the past for windows phone and
...windows...and...one.
And, then this policy for universe...windows ten universe...
And, twenty-two up so ...
A simple level all of the pri windows ten
...types.
So, all of the.
Windows h x xhtml
...the silverlight types and xna and native hybrids so on and we had
...windows phone for windows ten they have the same policy they've always had this is an
app compact issue we don't change their policy they stay as they were they get all
the same behaviors is...before universal...
Of different policy in some cases any very slightly different
...based on the old.
Build windows phone...policies and, but,
extended and brought forward for the range of different skews.
So, the policies are...if you build a wmv windows
...up...build a windows ten
app universe labs they hope they will have slightly different policy on most devices
any slightly different in some cases is not some cases same and...we don't
...at all so there's no policy.
Pre windows ten desktop up so
...windows ten immersive apps for windows eight and
...point one they didn't have any memory caps example so they continue not have any memory
cams...when thirty-two apps they do not have any memory caps?
Because again we want to maintain
...components we didn't break any of those things just because we have a new model.
So, policy...across these different dimensions.
And, finally.
What's the take away from this hyper...enough information and,
reading between the lines hopefully you've got the message that there
is a very large matrix of...resource
constraints memory caps cpu quotas lifetime
quotas access to device resources so on it's a very large matrix
varies across multiple dimensions the device configuration the skew.
So, on if you want to...reasonable obsessive different devices
and different skews you need to pay attention you need to query the system find out what
you actually running...my running on a desktop hundred-twenty...mi running on a mobile
device size and type of or mi running on t device.
So,...the system find out what's,
what's available to you to...behavior accordingly and,
then also listen foot change notifications when your memory
...changes all the network connectivity changes or cpu
...changes new energy consumption changes
listen for notifications and again act accordingly
...behavior thoughtful downhill behavior...core
...depending on the notification so in this way you will be able to target the
...possible range in a way that seamless to the users that you'll
behave appropriate on each device without being horribly slow...one device and
super-fast on another device you continue behavior which might mean in a tuning the feature
...play might mean chaining the resolution of your graphics images or, you know,...
also medications you can take once you've...the system to find out what you're running on.
Well, and, thank you for watching.